{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In Strasbourg in 1988, this leader proposed a non-nuclear “zone of peace” that banned Chinese immigration to his homeland. This winner of the 1989 Nobel Peace Prize currently lives in Dharamshala, India, having fled after a 1959 uprising was put down by the Chinese. This man was chosen as the 14th to hold his position at the age of 2 as the reincarnation of Thubten Gyatso. For ten points, name this exiled religious figure, the leader of Tibetan Buddhism.",
      "answer": "the 14th Dalai Lama or Jetsun Jamphel Ngawang Lobsang Yeshe Tenzin Gyatso"
    },
    {
      "question": "On the campaign trail, this politician struggled to answer questions about a golf trip with Paula Parkinson. This politician claimed that Murphy Brown’s role as a single mother hastened America’s moral decline a month prior to misspelling potato as a spelling bee judge. In a debate, Lloyd Bentsen stated that this man was “no Jack Kennedy”. For ten points, name this oft-criticized vice president who served under George H.W. Bush.",
      "answer": "James Danforth “Dan” Quayle"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man and Mario Amaya were shot by the author of the SCUM Manifesto in 1968. This man’s creation of 15 images of a totaled car sold for $105 million in 2013. This artist of Silver Car Crash directed a film of the Empire State Building over the course of six hours and made numerous silkscreen images of bottles of Coca-Cola, Campbell soup cans, and other consumer goods. The Factory was the primary studio of, for ten points, what American pop artist?",
      "answer": "Andy Warhol or Andrew Warhola"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man relaxed his troops by noting the presence of his soldier, Gisgo, at one of his victories. This man lost his right eye while travelling over the Apennines and the Arno to reach one of his battles, where his forces defeated the army of Gaius Flaminius. The Fabian strategy was used to delay this man’s forces, and after his victory at the Battle of Cannae he was finally defeated at the Battle of Zama by his chief rival, Scipio Africanus. For ten points, name this Carthaginian general who fought Rome during the Second Punic War.",
      "answer": "Hannibal Barca"
    },
    {
      "question": "PETA has protested a ritual held one day before this holiday in which a chicken is swung over the head, then donated to charity. The Ne´ılah is read on this day, the tenth of Tishrei, which includes five prayer services and fasting. In 1973, this holiday was marred by a surprise attack in the Sinai Peninsula by Egypt against Israel. For ten points, name this Jewish Day of Atonement, the holiest day of the Jewish year.",
      "answer": "Yom Kippur or Day of Atonement before mention"
    },
    {
      "question": "E´douard Ren´e de Laboulaye proposed this sculpture, for which fundraising was done by Joseph Pulitzer and by Emma Lazarus, who wrote the sonnet “The New Colossus” for it. Broken chains are near this sculpture’s feet; the subject is carrying a tablet inscribed with America’s independence date and is holding a torch. For ten points, name this Frederic Bartholdi sculpture that stands in New York Harbor.",
      "answer": "Statue of Liberty or Liberty Enlightening the World"
    },
    {
      "question": "A rebellion against Ottoman incursions into this modern-day country in the late 1400s was led by the nobleman Skanderbeg. An Italian invasion during the buildup to World War II ended monarchical rule in this nation under King Zog, and this Southeast European country was ruled for much of the Cold War by the Communist regime of Enver Hoxha [HAW-ja]. For ten points, name this Balkan nation whose capital is Tirana.",
      "answer": "Republic of Albania or Republika e Shqiperise"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author wrote the short stories “The Sing-Song of Old Man Kangaroo” and “How the Leopard got His Spots.” The title character of one of this man’s works is used as a pawn in the “Great Game” between Russia and Britain, and a poem by this man encourages a certain group of people to “send for the best ye breed”. For ten points, name this Victorian author of “The White Man’s Burden,” Kim, and Just-So Stories.",
      "answer": "Rudyard Kipling or Joseph Rudyard Kipling"
    },
    {
      "question": "This president tried to send John Slidell to negotiate the purchase of territory in modern New Mexico. He sent Nicholas Trist to negotiate a treaty that replaced the Nueces River with the Rio Grande as a national border and ended the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this “dark horse” president during whose term the United States gained territory in present-day California.",
      "answer": "James K. Polk"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man claimed to feel “nothing” after returning from exile following the White Revolution. In one speech, he referred to the United States as the “wounded snake” and the “Great Satan.” This leader’s objections to the novel The Satanic Verses led him to issue a fatwa against author Salman Rushdie. For ten points, name this Shia Islamic cleric who replaced Reza Pahlavi in the 1979 Iranian Revolution.",
      "answer": [
        "Ayatollah Khomeini",
        "Ruhollah Khomeini",
        "Imam Khomeini"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The perioikoi were a class of freed people living in this city, and the mothakes were raised as citizens of this city. This city’s navy, led by Peisander, was destroyed at the Battle of Cnidus, part of the Corinthian War that this city fought alongside the Peloponnesian League. The Agiad and Eurypontid lines ruled this city, whose legendary founder and lawgiver was Lycurgus. For ten points, name this militaristic Greek city-state, the long-time rival to Athens.",
        "answer": [
          "Sparta",
          "Lacedaemon"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Sparta’s victory in the First Messanian War led to a large increase in the population of these people, subjugated slaves made to work for Spartans. They were killed at will during the crypteia.",
        "answer": "helots"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this show’s third season, an Aqua Net design showing four people riding in a convertible has to be remade following the John F. Kennedy assassination. This show’s protagonist assumes his commanding officer’s identity during the Korean War, and discusses the meaning of nostalgia while delivering a sales pitch for the Kodak Carousel slide projector. For ten points, name this recently-ended AMC drama starring Jon Hamm as 1960s advertising executive Don Draper.",
        "answer": "Mad Men"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The final episode of Mad Men closes with the real-life 1971 “Hilltop” commercial, in which a group of young people sing that they would “like to buy the world” this popular beverage.",
        "answer": [
          "Coca-Cola",
          "Coke"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One literary work set during this period is Primo Levi’s The Periodic Table, part of which details his time at Fossoli di Carpi. The first graphic novel to win a Pulitzer Prize is set during this event and stylizes the antagonists as cats and pigs. Art Spiegelman’s Maus and a book by Elie Wiesel partially set at Buchenwald are also set during this period. For ten points, name this event, the setting of Night, which is partially set at Auschwitz.",
        "answer": "the Holocaust"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Diary of Anne Frank is set in this city until its characters are deported to Bergen-Belsen concentration camp.",
        "answer": "Amsterdam"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Russian Ukase of 1821 violated this national policy with regards to Alaska. George Canning had originally proposed a joint effort to enact this decree, but it was rejected by John Quincy Adams. Richard Olney cited this policy to justify interference with British negotiations in the Venezuela Crisis. For ten points, name this decree opposing European intervention in the Western Hemisphere, named for the successor to James Madison.",
        "answer": "Monroe Doctrine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This President’s Corollary to the Monroe Doctrine allowed for intervention by the United States to overthrow “chronic wrongdoing” in Latin America.",
        "answer": "Theodore “Teddy” Roosevelt"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One leader of this group reportedly lost his right eye at the Battle of Arghandab in 1987 and died of tuberculosis in 2013. This group did not announce that leader’s death until 2015 and is disputing reports that his replacement, Akhtar Mansoor, was killed in December 2015. Mullah Muhammad Omar led this organization and was President of its home country until 2001’s Operation Enduring Freedom. For ten points, name this Islamic insurgent group that once controlled Afghanistan.",
        "answer": "Taliban"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Taliban is funded largely by smuggling of this substance, which is harvested by making small cuts in poppy seed pods and then processed into a variety of drugs, including heroin.",
        "answer": "opium"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "According to legend, at the premiere of one of these works, Hector Berlioz stormed the stage to take the baton from the conductor during the Tuba Mirum section. One of these works interweaves the Lacrimosa with Wilfred Owen’s poem “Futility,” while another of these works chose to use the Luther Bible, a German text. An unfinished one of these by Mozart was sung in January 1964, two months after the death of John Kennedy. For ten points, name these religious musical compositions for the dead.",
        "answer": "requiem mass"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This composer of the aforementioned German Requiem also composed a famous lullaby.",
        "answer": "Johannes Brahms"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Joel Klein was the leading prosecutor in a case involving this company, which involved restrictive licensing agreements with OEMs. It was forced to share its APIs with third-party companies in the settlement of its case. Paul Maritz, an employee of this company, was quoted as wanting to “extinguish” Netscape during testimony concerning this company’s potential monopolistic behavior in its bundling of Internet Explorer. For ten points, name this software company founded by Bill Gates.",
        "answer": [
          "Microsoft",
          "U.S. v. Microsoft"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This lawyer represented the states in U.S. v. Microsoft before being appointed to the D.C. Circuit in 2003. This Supreme Court justice typically votes with Scalia, Thomas, and Alito to uphold conservative rulings.",
        "answer": "John G. Roberts"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A coin struck in this city with a fleur de lis on one side and John the Baptist on the other became the most popular coin for transactions in Europe in the 14th century. The castato system was instituted in this city after a successful war against the Visconti of Milan, and this city was ruled by Piero the Unfortunate before being taken over by a Dominican friar in 1494. For ten points, name this Italian city, ruled for a brief time by Girolamo Savonarola and home to the Medici family.",
        "answer": "Florence"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Savonarola conducted one of these events on Mardi Gras in Florence to get rid of thousands of books, paintings, and cosmetics.",
        "answer": [
          "bonfire",
          "Bonfire of the Vanities"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Oil!",
      "prompt": "In the history of oil, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "founder of the Standard Oil Company.",
          "answer": "John Davidson Rockefeller"
        },
        {
          "question": "body of water where the Deepwater Horizon exploded in 2010.",
          "answer": "Gulf of Mexico"
        },
        {
          "question": "pipeline whose proposed Canada-to-Nebraska expasion was rejected by President Obama in 2015.",
          "answer": [
            "Keystone",
            "Keystone XL"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "oil tanker that crashed into Prince William Sound in 1989.",
          "answer": "Exxon Valdez"
        },
        {
          "question": "muckraker who wrote The History of the Standard Oil Company for McClure’s.",
          "answer": "Ida Minerva Tarbell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wyoming oil field leased to Harry Sinclair by Albert Fall in 1922.",
          "answer": "Teapot Dome"
        },
        {
          "question": "concept, coined by M. King Hubbert, that oil will eventually cease to be economically viable, leading to a stark decline in oil production.",
          "answer": "peak oil"
        },
        {
          "question": "oil well drilled near Titusville, Pennsylvania in 1859, which triggered a boom in commercial oil drilling.",
          "answer": "Drake Well"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Otto Von Bismarck",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "country provoked into a war that led to the collapse of the Second Empire and the declaration of the Third Republic in Paris.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Emperor of Germany, under whom Bismarck served as Chancellor.",
          "answer": "Wilhelm I"
        },
        {
          "question": "kingdom that Bismarck served before Germany’s founding.",
          "answer": "Prussia"
        },
        {
          "question": "two substances that will “solve the great questions of the day,” according to Bismarck.",
          "answer": "Blood and Iron or Eisen und Blut"
        },
        {
          "question": "religion targeted by Adalbert Falk’s May Laws.",
          "answer": "Roman Catholicism"
        },
        {
          "question": "term for the anti-religious policies that included the May Laws.",
          "answer": "Kulturkampf"
        },
        {
          "question": "term used to describe Bismarck’s pragmatic diplomacy which focused on power balancing.",
          "answer": "Realpolitik"
        },
        {
          "question": "region ceded to Prussia and Austria in the Treaty of Vienna after a war with Denmark—",
          "answer": "Schleswig-Holstein"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Henry VIII",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "total number of wives he had.",
          "answer": "6"
        },
        {
          "question": "first woman he married.",
          "answer": "Catherine of Aragon"
        },
        {
          "question": "second woman he married, who bore him Elizabeth I?",
          "answer": "Anne Boleyn"
        },
        {
          "question": "adviser and author of Utopia who was executed for treason.",
          "answer": "Sir Thomas More"
        },
        {
          "question": "title bestowed upon him by Pope Leo X after writing Defense of the Seven Sacraments",
          "answer": "Defender of the Faith or Fidei defensor"
        },
        {
          "question": "church he founded after his excommunication by the Pope.",
          "answer": "Church of England or Anglican Church"
        },
        {
          "question": "act passed by Parliament that declared him the head of that Church?",
          "answer": "Act of Supremacy"
        },
        {
          "question": "field where Henry VIII met Francis I of France over three weeks in summer 1520.",
          "answer": "Field of the Cloth of Gold"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Dickinson, the author of Letters from a Pennsylvania Farmer, refused to sign this document. Charles Thomson presided over the meeting that produced this document, and sent its final, handwritten copy to John Dunlap for (20 pts)",
        "printing. Richard Henry Lee introduced the resolution creating this document, and Roger Sherman and Benjamin (10 pts)",
        "Franklin served on the Committee of Five that edited this text. For ten points, name this document whose Preamble asserts that “We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal,” written by Thomas Jefferson."
      ],
      "answer": "Declaration of Independence"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country defeated Count von Bennigsen at the Battle of Friedland, leading to a treaty signed on a raft in the Neman River, the Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Tilsit. This country burned down a capital city after the Battle of Borodino, then retreated from “General Winter” and the (10 pts)",
        "Cossacks when it couldn’t defeat Alexander I’s Russia. For ten points, name this country whose Grande Arm´ee was led by Napoleon Bonaparte."
      ],
      "answer": "France"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William Cosby was the target of one man who made his fortune through the sale of these entities. An account titled “Heed Their Rising Voices” was published by one organization that created these entities and led to a (20 pts)",
        "lawsuit that established the standard of “actual malice” with regards to libel. John (10 pts)",
        "Peter Zenger, a printer of these documents, was acquitted in a case that established truth as a defense against libel. For ten points, name these periodicals, the subject of the court case New York Times v. Sullivan."
      ],
      "answer": "newspapers"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One scientist with this last name proposed the fission theory of the moon. Another scientist with this last name described the inheritance of acquired characteristics in the 1794 work Zoonomia. Another scientist with this last name wrote (20 pts)",
        "The Descent of Man and names a group of finch species he saw on the Galapagos Islands during his voyage on the (10 pts)",
        "HMS Beagle. For ten points, give the surname of the author of On the Origin of Species, who showed natural selection was a means of evolution."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Darwin",
        "George Darwin, Erasmus Darwin",
        "Charles Darwin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader allowed for the publishing of Alexander Solzhenitsyn’s One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich and he attempted to increase agricultural production by starting the (20 pts)",
        "Virgin Lands Campaign. This leader reportedly banged his shoe on a table during a U.N. Conference and 4 years earlier had told Western diplomats “we will (10 pts)",
        "bury you!” He complained about his predecessor’s personality cult in the “Secret Speech” and was replaced in his highest position by Leonid Brezhnev. For ten points, name this Soviet leader during the Cuban Missile Crisis."
      ],
      "answer": "Nikita Khrushchev"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city’s Iberville Projects were built on the site of its red-light district, which was shut down in 1917. This city’s oldest neighborhood, just east of Storyville, features buildings with distinctive (20 pts)",
        "ironwork galleries and balconies. Another neighborhood in this city, which lies downriver of the Industrial Canal, suffered (10 pts)",
        "catastrophic damage in a 2005 storm that breached the levees of the Mississippi River. The Lower Ninth Ward and the French Quarter are in, for ten points, what Louisiana city?"
      ],
      "answer": "New Orleans, Louisiana"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Victor Espinoza and Bob Baffert’s work with this athlete resulted in a runner-up finish at Saratoga and nine victories. Sports Illustrated was criticized for naming (20 pts)",
        "Serena Williams its 2015 Sportsman of the Year over this athlete, who completed a Grand Slam with his (10 pts)",
        "Breeders’ Cup victory. For ten points, name this horse who won the Belmont, Preakness, and Kentucky Derby to complete horse racing’s first Triple Crown since 1978."
      ],
      "answer": "American Pharoah"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Rexford Tugwell served as this territory’s governor during World War II, shortly before two of its nationalists killed policeman Leslie Coffelt in an attempt to assassinate Harry (20 pts)",
        "Truman. Its current governor, Alejandro Garcia Padilla, believes that it would turn into a “Latin American ghetto” if the (10 pts)",
        "statehood movement were to succeed. For ten points, name this U.S. Commonwealth with capital San Juan, where 834,000 citizens voted support for making it the 51st U.S. state in 2012."
      ],
      "answer": "Puerto Rico"
    }
  ]
}